Guide to the Sir John Orde Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sir John Orde papers
1789-1878
1798-1805
OSB MSS 133
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.38
(17 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, order books, signal logs, and related naval and Admiralty papers that document aspects of Sir John Orde's naval career, primarily during the Napoleonic Wars. The collection provides substantial information related to Orde's bitter disputes with Admiral of the Fleet John Jervis, Lord St. Vincent; his rivalry with Horatio Nelson; and his professional frustration with the workings of the Admiralty Board and its bureaucracy. The collection also contains information on Orde's tenure as governor of Dominica and his suppression of mutinies at Plymouth and on board the Princess Royal. In addition to Lord St. Vincent and Horatio Nelson, correspondents include Baron Gambier, Sir John Duckworth, Sir Evan Nepean, Viscount Melville, and other contemporary naval and political figures.
Orde, John, Sir, 1751-1824
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lot 119 from Christie's sale of Wednesday, 7 June 2006. The Sir John Orde Papers were purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sir John Orde, 1751-1824
Sir John Orde, first baronet, naval officer and politician, was born in Morpeth, England in 1751, the youngest son of John Orde (circa 1704-circa 1786) and the brother of Thomas Orde-Powlett, first Lord Bolton. Orde entered the navy in 1766; in 1773 he was promoted to lieutenant; and, during the American War of Independence, he was promoted to captain and took part in the reduction of Charlestown and the capture of several American ships. In 1781 he married Margaret Emma (1759-1790), daughter of Richard Stevens of Charlestown.
After the war, Orde was appointed governor of Dominica, where he governed successfully enough to be awarded a baronetcy in 1790; but when war broke out with France in 1793, Orde returned to the navy. Promoted to Rear Admiral in 1795, he served in the Mediterranean Fleet under John Jervis, Earl St. Vincent. However, a complaint that St. Vincent wrongly attributed to Orde sparked an acrimonious dispute between them, resulting in St. Vincent's command that Orde return to England; Orde's request that St. Vincent be court-martialed; his frustrated attempts to challenge St. Vincent to a duel; and pamphlets that Orde circulated privately defending his actions.
In 1804, having been promoted to Vice Admiral several years earlier, he commanded a successful blockade of Cadiz on Spain's entry into the war. Following complaints by Horatio Nelson, however, that Orde's blockade restricted his own opportunities to obtain prize money, Orde requested to return to England despite the ongoing war, occasioning another scandal.
In 1805 Orde was promoted to Admiral of the Blue, in 1809 to Admiral of the White, and in 1814 to Admiral of the Red. From 1807 to 1812 he served as Member of Parliament for Yarmouth. He died in 1824 after a long illness and was buried in Hanwell, Middlesex. His second wife, Jane (circa 1773-1829), daughter of John Frere, died in 1829; their son, John Powlett Orde, inherited the baronetcy on his father's death.
For further information, see Orde's entry in the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.
Scope and Contents
The Orde Papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, order books, signal logs, and related naval and Admiralty papers that document aspects of Sir John Orde's naval career, primarily during the Napoleonic Wars. The papers span the dates 1789-1878, but the bulk of the material dates from between 1796 and 1805, and provides substantial information related to Orde's bitter disputes with the Admiral of the Fleet John Jervis, Lord St. Vincent; his rivalry with Horatio Nelson; and his career frustration with the entire Admiralty Board. The collection also contains information on his tenure as governor of Dominica and his suppression of mutinies at Plymouth and on the Princess Royal. The Orde Papers offer valuable insight into the Royal Navy's organization and actions during a crucial period of the Napoleonic Wars, as well as into the often conflicting professional agendas of the individual officers under its command.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Letterbooks, Order Books, and Orders; III. Signal Books and Logs; and IV. Admiralty Papers.
Admirals -- Great Britain; Mutinies -- Great Britain; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815 -- Blockades; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815 -- Naval operations, British; Naval battles -- Great Britain; Prizes (Property captured at sea) -- Great Britain; Sea control -- Great Britain; Signals and signaling; Great Britain -- History -- 1789-1820; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 18th century; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 19th century; Mediterranean Sea -- History, Naval; Logs (records); Bridport, Alexander Hood, Viscount, 1726-1814; Cornwallis, William, Sir, 1744-1819; Duckworth, John Thomas, Sir; Gambier, James Gambier, Baron, 1756-1833; Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, 1759-1834; Howe, Richard Howe, Earl, 1726-1799; Dundas, Henry, 1742-1811; Nelson, Horatio Nelson, Viscount, 1758-1805; Nepean, Evan, Sir, 1751-1822; Orde, John, Sir, 1751-1824; St. Vincent, John Jervis, Viscount, 1735-1823; Young, William, Sir, 1749-1815; Great Britain. Admiralty; Great Britain. Royal Navy; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Management; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Officers; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Order-books; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Signaling
- Correspondence, 1789-1818; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence, has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of Orde's correspondence consists of responses from naval officers, politicians, and other public figures to Orde's 1798 pamphlet describing his feud with Admiral St.Vincent. Correspondents on this subject include Alexander Hood,Viscount Bridport; John Pitt, Earl of Chatham; Richard Carr, Sir Glyn; Charles Lennox, Duke of Richmond and Lennox; and Richard Creyke. Many correspondents mention their prior knowledge of the dispute from newspaper accounts. In addition, the collection includes an official letter from Sir Evan Nepean to Admiral St. Vincent informing him of the King's command that he refuse any challenge to a duel from Orde.
  The remaining correspondence primarily concerns Orde's other naval and political activities, especially in relation to his dissatisfaction with aspects of his naval career. An official letter by William, Baron Grenville in 1790 addresses colonial complaints against Orde during his governorship of Dominica. Several letters by James, Baron Gambier commend Orde's handling of the 1797 mutiny at Plymouth. The correspondence also includes numerous letters from St. Vincent himself, consisting of both official Admiralty correspondence with Orde and personal letters discussing military tactics. Other letters from St. Vincent admonish Orde for his dissatisfaction with Horatio Nelson's appointment as commander of a detached squadron to pursue Napoleon; order Orde to return to England in the Blenheim in 1798; and trace the growth of their quarrel. Several 1799 letters, including those by Sir William Parker and George Purvis, discuss the controversy over the division of the Nile Prize money.
  The collection also contains several letters and drafts by Orde himself, including copies of notes to his wife written from the Princess Royal in 1798, which comment on his growing disagreement with St. Vincent. Copies of correspondence between Orde and Nelson detail Nelson's response to Orde's pamphlet and his defense of the Admiralty's decision to favor him with the Mediterranean command. Finally, a letter to Henry Dundas, Viscount Melville in 1805 discusses Orde's blockade at Cadiz and Nelson's complaints concerning it, as well as Orde's request to be allowed to resign from his command.
  - Empty folder, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ackland, Dudley, 1800, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Affleck, Philip, 1798 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agnew, Robert Vans, 1755-1809, 1801 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allott, Dr., 1802, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aplin, Peter, 1752-1817, 1798-1810 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aylmer, F., 1824 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baker, Thomas, Sir, 1771?-1845, 1797 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barham, Charles, Middleton, Baron, 1726-1813, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barlow, Robert, Sir, 1757-1843, 1798-1801 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bates, Mr., 1798 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berkeley, George Cranfield, Sir, 1753-1818, 1798 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bickerton, Richard, Sir, 1759-1832, 1799 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bigges, Jemima, circa 1799 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bolton, Thomas Orde-Powlett, Baron, 1740-1807, 1799-1805 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Boone, Jonathan, 1799, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Booth, Frederick, 1798 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bridport, Alexander Hood, Viscount, 1726-1814, 1797, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brereton, Robert, 1799 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bridges, Richard, 1799 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bruce, James, 1802 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bursey, J., 1811 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Caldwell, Benjamin, 1739-1820, 1798 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Canning, George, 1806-1810 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Carysfort, John Proby, Earl, 1751-1828, 1798 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cathcart, William Cathcart, Earl, 1755-1843, 1798 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chatham, John Pitt, Earl, 1756-1835, 1798, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chinnery, William, 1810 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clarendon, John Villiers, Earl, 1757-1838, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cobbett, William, 1763-1835, 1802 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Collingwood, Cuthbert, Baron, 1748-1810, 1793-1798 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Colpoys, John, Sir, 1742-1821, 1797, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Conant, N., 1800 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cornwallis, William, Sir, 1744-1819, 1798-1818, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cosby, Philip, 1730?-1808, 1798 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Costobadie, Jacob, 1758-1828, 1801, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Craven, Charles, 1799, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Creyke, Richard, 1746-1826, 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Croker, J. W., 1818 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Curtis, Roger, 1746-1816, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Cuyler, Cornelius, 1740?-1819, 1798-1802 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Daniell, Thomas, 1799 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - De Mazzaredo, Jose, 1745-1812, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dick, John, 1799 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dickson, William, d. 1803, 1797, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Donne, Henry, 1804 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Draper, John, 1799 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Duffey, James John, 1797 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Duncan, Mary, Lady, 1723-1806, 1797 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Duckworth, John, Sir, 1747-1817, 1790-1800 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Ducie, Francis Reynolds Moreton, Baron, 1739-1808, 1798 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Eldon, John Scott, Earl, 1751-1838, 1807-1812 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Exmouth, Edward Pellew, Viscount, 1757-1833, 1797 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Fawcett, William, Sir, 1727-1804, 1798 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Fawkener, William, 1750-1817, 1798, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Frazer, Simon, 1798, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Frere, John, 1740-1807, 1799 October 9 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Gambier, James Gambier, Baron, 1756-1833, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - George, Rupert, Sir, 1749-1823, 1798 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Glasse, Samuel, 1734-1811, 1799 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Glynn, Richard Carr, Sir, 1755-1838, 1798 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Goodall, Samuel Granston, d. 1801, 1799 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Gower, Erasmus, Sir, 1742-1814, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, 1759-1834, 1790-1806 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Hamilton, Rear Admiral, 1799 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Hamond, Andrew, Sir, 1738-1828, 1789-1805 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Harvey, Henry, Sir, 1737-1810, 1799 March 20 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Haslewood, William, 1806 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Holloway, John, 1744-1826, 1799 March (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Hood, Samuel Hood, Viscount, 1724-1816, 1798-1802 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Hope, William Johnstone, Sir, 1766-1831?, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Hotchkiss, Charles, 1802 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Hotham, William Hotham, Baron, 1736-1813, 1798-1805 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Howe, Mary (Hartop), Lady, 1732-1800, 1798, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Howe, Richard Howe, Earl, 1726-1799, 1780-1799 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Howe, William Howe, Viscount, 1729-1814, 1799 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Huskisson, William, 1770-1830, 1798 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Keats, Richard Goodwin, Sir, 1757-1834, 1804 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Keith, George Elphinstone, Viscount, 1746-1823, 1799-1804, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - King, Richard, Sir, 1730-1806, 1798 December 9 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Knowles, Charles Henry, Sir, 1754-1831, 1799 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, Marquess of, 1780-1863, 1807 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquess of, 1737-1805, 1797-1802 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Laurie, Robert, Sir, 1738-1804, 1798-1802 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Lloyd, Major General, 1798 November 22 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Louis, Thomas, Sir, 1758-1807, 1804 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Mallet, John Lewis, 1775-1861, 1810-1811 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Manning, William, 1763-1835, 1798 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Marsden, William, 1754-1836, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Matra, James Mario, 1746?-1806, 1805 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Melville, Henry Dundas, Viscount, 1742-1811, 1791-1813 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Metcalfe, Thomas, 1797 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Milbanke, Mark, Sir, 1724-1805, 1798 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Mitford, John, 1798 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Moira, Francis Rawdon-Hastings, Earl, 1754-1826, 1799 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Montagu, George, Sir, 1750-1829, 1799-1802 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Mulgrave, Henry Phipps, Earl, 1755-1831, 1798 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Nelson, Horatio Nelson, Viscount, 1758-1805, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Nepean, Evan, Sir, 1752-1822, 1799-1803, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Northumberland, Hugh Percy, Duke, 1742-1817, 1798 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Nugent, Charles Edmund, Sir, 1759-1844, 1798 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Nussey, John, 1760-1826, 1799, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - O'Hara, Charles, 1740-1802, 1799 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Ommanney, Edward, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Ommanney, F. W., circa 1804 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Ord, A., undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Orde, John, 1802 June 24 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Orde, John, Sir, 1751-1824, 1798-1805 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Orde, William, 1798, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Parker, Edward, 1798 April 28 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Parker, Peter, Sir, 1721-1811, 1797 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Parker, William, Sir, 1743-1802, 1798, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Parley, Thomas, Sir, 1799, undated (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Pattison, James, 1723-1805, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Patton, Philip, 1739-1815, 1799 February 5 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Peareth, William, 1734-1810, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Pelham, George, 1766-1827, 1798-1816 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Pennington, William, 1800 August 19 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Perceval, Spencer, 1762-1812, 1810-1811 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Peyton, Joseph, d. 1804, 1798 November 17 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Portland, William Cavendish-Bentinck, Duke, 1738-1809, 1798 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Purvis, George, d. 1826, 1799 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Pulteney, Daniel, 1799 November 24 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Radstock, William Waldegrave, Baron, 1753-1825, undated (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Reeves, John, 1798-1802 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Richmond and Lennox, Charles Lennox, Duke, 1735-1806, 1798, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Robinson, John, 1799-1802 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Rose, George, 1744-1818, 1799-1802 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Ryder, D., 1798 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Salt, G., 1802 June 26 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Saumarez, James Saumarez, Baron, 1757-1836, 1798-1804 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Savage, Henry, 1799 December 5 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Saxton, Charles, Sir, 1732-1808, 1798 December 19 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Schomberg, Isaac, 1753-1813, 1802 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Seymour, Henry, Lord, 1746-1830, 1797-1799 (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Sidmouth, Henry Addington, Viscount, 1757-1844, 1798 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Sisson, Mr., 1802 July 14 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Smelt, Leonard, 1798, 1800 (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Smith, Joseph, 1798 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Spry, William, 1734-1802, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - St. Vincent, John Jervis, Earl, 1735-1823, 1797-1798 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Steele, Mr., 1798 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - Stirling, Charles, Sir, 1760-1833, 1799 December 19 (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - Strange, James, 1802 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Sydney, Thomas Townshend, Viscount, 1732-1800, 1798 December 17 (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Temple, Francis, 1802 (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Thurlow, Edward Thurlow, Baron, 1731-1806, 1798 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Wade, Mr., 1799 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Wallace, James, Sir, 1731-1803, 1798, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Walpole, Robert, 1799 January 12 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Warren, John, Sir, 1753-1822, 1797, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Wells, Thomas, 1797 January 19 (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - Wharton, Robert, 1810 (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - Whitby, Captain, d. ca. 1805, 1802 June (Box 3, Folder 154)
  - William IV, King of Great Britain, 1765-1837, undated (Box 3, Folder 155)
  - Wodehouse, John Wodehouse, Baron, 1741-1834, 1798 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 156)
  - Yeo, James, d. 1825, 1799 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 157)
  - Yorke, Charles Philip, 1764-1834, 1810-1812, undated (Box 3, Folder 158)
  - Young, William, Sir, 1751-1821, 1799-1806 (Box 3, Folder 159)
- Letterbooks, Order Books, and Other Naval Documents, 1794-1878; Series II; 8.66; (10 boxes)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Letterbooks and Order Books and Other Naval Documents
  Series II consists primarily of orders and other correspondence from the Admiralty Office to Orde and from Orde to his subordinates, dated between 1794-1805; and Orde's business papers, dated between 1799 and 1817.
  Almost all of the letterbooks and order books contain both orders to Orde, and, dos-a-dos, Orde's responses or subsequent commands to his own subordinates. These books record naval commands at Gibraltar and Lisbon; positions of enemy ships, captures of ships, and details of prizes; personnel changes; and negotiations regarding the exchange of prisoners of war. Orde's letters are frequently of an administrative nature, requesting provisions and providing surveys of stores, as well as asking for updates on the hospital at Gibraltar. A significant portion of the correspondence refers to command of the Princess Royal, particularly supression of a planned mutiny in support of the Irish Rebellion of 1798.
  This series also contains the official documents appointing Orde to Commander-in-Chief in 1804 and Admiral of the Red in 1814; instructions and regulations regarding flags and signals; diagrams and lists of battle positions; and a pamphlet of regulations governing behavior, dress, and duties on board ships under Orde's command. Additionally, numerous documents are devoted to recording the details of the vessels captured by Orde, including ships' names; numbers of men, tons, and guns on board; their origins and destinations; and their cargoes. Other documents concern the prize money from such captures, including a list of expected proceeds from detained vessels and an account of shares paid to various members of his squadron.
  Financial papers include accounts relating to the Audit Office investigation of the charges that he continued to hold public monies from Dominica after his term as governor had ended.
  Finally, this series contains two copies of Orde's defense of his request to be called home from Cadiz in 1805.
  - Letterbooks and Order Books
    - Letterbook, 1794-1797 (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - Admiralty Letters Received Between the 18th May and 22d May 1797 at Plymouth (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Order book, 1794-1798 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Letters to the Admiral, 1797-1798 (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Letterbook, 1804-1805 (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - Letterbook, 1804-1805 (Box 9, Folder 165)
    - Order Book, 1804-1805 (Box 10, Folder 166)
    - Order Book, 1804-1805 (Box 11, Folder 167)
    - Secret Orders Admiralty Admirals, 1804-1805 (Box 12, Folder 168)
  - Other Naval Documents
    - Accounts of captured vessels and prize money, 1797-1809 (Box 13, Folder 169)
    - Audit Office investigation of Orde, 1810 (Box 13, Folder 170)
    - Cadiz incident: statements by Orde defending his actions at Cadiz and his request for recall to England, circa 1805 (Box 13, Folder 171)
    - Financial papers: accounts and receipts, 1799-1817 (Box 13, Folder 172-176)
    - List of ships in which Orde served, undated (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - Naval instructions and regulations, 1799-1805, undated (Box 13, Folder 178-179)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1798 (Box 13, Folder 180)
    - Official documents concerning Orde's appoinments, 1804, 1814 (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - "Philosophical Papers" excerpt, undated (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Notes and wrappers, 1797-1878, undated (Box 13, Folder 183)
- Signal books and Logs, 1799-1806; Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  The series consists of chronologically arranged signal books and logs, dated between 1799-1806. These are primarily printed instructions, many with handwritten annotations as well as colored illustrations and diagrams of battle formations as dictated by signal flags. The collection also includes two signal logs for HMS Glory.
  - Night Signals and Instructions for the Conduct of Ships of War, 1799 (Box 14, Folder 184)
  - Telegraphic Signals; or Marine Vocabulary, 1803 (Box 14, Folder 185)
  - Signal logs for HMS Glory, 1804-1805 (Box 14, Folder 186)
  - Signal-Book for the Ships of War, 1805 (Box 14, Folder 187)
  - Signals for Ships of War, circa 1806 (Box 15, Folder 188)
  - Signal book for flags, undated (Box 15, Folder 189)
  - Instructions for Making Numerical Signals, undated (Box 15, Folder 190)
  - Lord Howe's Signals, undated (Box 15, Folder 191)
- Admiralty Papers, 1791-1824; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series IV, Admiralty Papers ,consists primarily of naval materials peripheral to Orde.The series also contains two printed pamphlets defending Orde's actions in his feud with St. Vincent. Both pamphlets include copies of correspondence and are annotated in Orde's hand; the pamphlet dated 1802 also includes one page, copied in Orde's hand and bound in, of correspondence with St. Vincent.
  - An Act for Amending, Explaining, and Reducing into One Act of Parliament, the Laws Relating to the Government of His Majesty's Ships, Vessels, and Forces by Sea, 1794 (Box 16, Folder 192)
  - Copy of a Correspondence, etc. Between the Right Hon. the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, the Right Hon. the Earl St. Vincent, K. B. the Right Hon. Earl Spencer, K. G. and Vice-Admiral Sir J. Orde, Bart., 1802 (Box 16, Folder 193)